Inventory of the Anatoliĭ L'vovich Markov writings
Hoover Institution Archives
Anatoliĭ L'vovich Markov writings
1917-1962
XX738
Markov, Anatoliĭ L'vovich, b. 1893
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection consists of memoirs and other writings relating to Russian military operations in World War I and the Russian Revolution, subsequent anti-communist movements in the Soviet Union (including biographies of participants), Soviet agents in Egypt and police surveillance and prosecution of them, and Russian émigré affairs. military operations in World War I and the Russian Revolution, subsequent anti-communist movements in the Soviet Union (including biographies of participants), Soviet agents in Egypt and police surveillance and prosecution of them, and Russian émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives between 1983 and 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on microfilm.
Related Materials
Vladimir Konkordovich Abdank-Kossovskiĭ papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Anatoliĭ L'vovich Markov papers, 1933-1963, Columbia University Libraries, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Bakhmeteef Archives
Biographical Note
1893 Born, Kurskaia guberniia, Russia
1913 Graduated from the Voronezh Cadet Corps and Nicholas Cavalry School
1914-1915 Served in World War I and was wounded
1920-1951 Immigrated to Egypt, assigned to a major post in the police in Alexandria
1950 Author of Monasteries in the Desert
1952 Retired and moved to the U.S.; author of Events in Egypt
1961 Author of The Cadets and Cadets; died in San Francisco
Scope and Content of Collection
Anatoliĭ L'vovich Markov was a Russian writer, author of numerous articles, memoirs, short stories, and historical essays. He also wrote under the pseudonym Sharki.
The collection consists of Markov's writings from all periods of his life relating to Russian military operations in World War I and the Russian Revolution, subsequent anti-communist movements in the Soviet Union (including biographies of participants), Soviet agents in Egypt and the police surveillance and prosecution of them, and Russian émigré affairs. The articles contain information about life in the Russian colony in Egypt and history of the region as a whole, as well as about the Eastern Orthodox Church.
The writings include seven titled scrapbooks containing clippings on the White movement from Russian émigré periodicals published in the United States from 1956 to 1959, émigré memoirs compiled by A. Markov, as well as his published memoirs Rodnye Gnezda.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Anti-communist movements--Soviet Union.; Subversive activities--Egypt.; Secret service--Egypt.; Police--Egypt.; Communism--Egypt.; Espionage, Russian--Egypt.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Soviet Union--Biography.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.
Collection Contents
- "Entsiklopediia Belogo Dvizheniia," Vol. I-IV (Encyclopedia of the Russian White Movement), circa 1960 (Folder 1: 1-8)
- "V Bor'be s Krasnym D'iavolom" (Thirty-five years of service in Egyptian political police), 1960 (Folder 1: 9, Folder 2: 1-3)
- "Kavkazskaia Konnaia Tuzemnaia Diviziia v Voĭnu 1914-1918 gg." (Memoirs of participants and historical review of the Russian irregular army in the Caucasus), 1949 (Folder 2: 4-7)
  Typescript stamped by the press censor of Alexandria, Egypt
- "V Izgnanii" (Memoirs), 1959 (Folder 2: 8-10)
  Includes clippings and photographs
- "Ocherki Russkoĭ Smuty i Revoliutsii" (Essays on Russian turmoil and revolution), typescript, 1958 (Folder 2: 11, Folder 3: 1)
  Includes clippings of Markov's articles
- "Liudi Drevnego Blagochestiia" (The history of sectarianism in Russia), 1960 (Folder 3: 2-6)
- "Zapiski o Proshlom" (Memoirs by various authors), 1955
  - Volume I. Newspaper articles, Turkey-Egypt, 1917-1952 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Volume II. Newspaper articles, Alexandria, Egypt, 1933-1951 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Volume III. "Vospominaniia o Sluzhbe v Egipetskoĭ Politicheskoĭ Politsii, 1922-1943" (The memoirs of Markov?s Egyptian political police service), undated (Folder 4: 1)
- Rodnye Gnezda (memoirs), printed copy, 1962 (Folder 4: 2)
- "Entsiklopediia Belogo Dvizheniia," Vol. I-IV (Encyclopedia of the Russian White Movement), circa 1960 (Folder Microfilm Cabinet)